Hello everyone, this
is Dr. **** Zhang.
In this session,
you will learn basic
concepts related to
cardiac arrhythmia.
Here are the
session objectives.
These are the contents
you are expected to learn.
Here is the definition
of arrhythmia. Arrhythmia
is defined as not
normal sinus rhythm.
So first you have to know
what's normal sinus rhythm.
As we have learned,
normal heartbeat is
originated from the
sinus node with a rate in
the range of 60 to
100 beats per minute.
It should be regular
and follow the
normal conduction
sequence as shown here.
Any deviation from the normal
sinus rhythm is arrhythmia.
Note that some arrhythmia
could be physiological.
For example,
if you exercise,
you can have sinus tachycardia.
We'll focus on clinically
significant arrhythmia.
Here is the arrhythmia
classification and mechanisms.
Depending on the heart rate,
Arrhythmia can be classified
as Brady Arrhythmia
if the heart rate is less
than 60 beats per minute.
The number is for adults.
Brady Arrhythmia
is caused by either
conduction block and or
reduced automaticity.
If heart rate is more than
100 beats per minute, it's
defined as Tachy Arrhythmia.
Tachyallythmia can be
caused by one or more of
the following mechanisms
increased automaticity,
triggered activity, and reentry.
Reentry is considered
as the most common
mechanism for all
tachyallythmians.
For tachyallythmians,
depending on the sites where
the allysmians are
originated, they can be
classified as supraventricular
arrhythmias if they
are originated from a site
at his bundle or above.
Because supraventricular
arrhythmias are typically
associated with normal
ventricular activation,
unless there is a pre
-existing abnormality in
the ventricles, such as
bundle branch block, They
typically produce normal
narrow QRS complex,
so narrow QRS
tachycardia is the
feature of supraventricular
tachycardia.
Any alizomere originated
from a site below
the his bundle is
defined as ventricular
alizomere. Because in
ventricular arrhythmia,
the ventricular activation
will be abnormal,
it will produce an abnormal
widened QRS complex. Thus,
wide QRS tachycardia is
typically ventricular origin.
Listed here are the basic
arrhythmia mechanisms.
They are divided
into two categories.
First,
abnormal impulse
initiation. The
second is abnormal
impulse conduction.
Under abnormal impulse
initiation, they are
abnormal automaticity
and tricked activity.
Under abnormal automaticity,
they are altered
normal automaticity and
abnormal automaticity.
Under tricked activity,
they are early
after depolarization
and delayed after
depolarization .
On the abnormal
impulse conduction,
there are conduction
block and reentry.
Conduction block can happen
in different sites in
the heart, such as at the
sinus node atrial junction,
in the AV node, his bundle,
and the bundle branches.
Reentry can happen due to
structural or anatomical
abnormalities such as
the accessory pathways,
scar tissues,
or due to functional changes
without structural change.
We'll discuss each of these in
more detail in the
next few slides.
or altered normal
automaticity. The
normal heartbeat is
from the sinus node.
The altered normal
automaticity refers to
either increased or
decreased sinus rates. If
the sinus rate is above
100 beats per minute,
it's sinus tachycardia.
Sinus tachycardia is
usually secondary and
could be physiological.
For example,
sinus tachycardia can
be seen during exercise.
Sinus tachycardia can also be
secondary to disease
states like fever,
psilotoxicosis, etc.
There is a clinical
syndrome called inappropriate
sinus tachycardia,
seen in patients
without obvious causes.
If the sinus rate is
less than 60 beats
per minute, it's called
sinus bradycardia.
It can be physiological,
seen in at rest. Next,
pathological sinus
bradycardia is typically
seen in sick sinus
syndrome or 3S syndrome,
a degenerative
disease in cardiac
pacemaker conduction system.
Abnormal automaticity refers
to non-pacemaker cells
like atrium myocytes or
ventricular myocytes In certain
disease states, like ischemia,
hypoxia, inflammation,
the injured myocytes
gain automaticity.
Because in disease states,
the injured myocytes
cannot maintain normal
resting membrane potential.
potential. The resting
membrane potential
could rise, and if the
resting membrane potential
cannot drop below
the threshold,
the fast sodium channel will be
inactivated, as we have
discussed previously
in the action
potential lecture.
These cells could be
activated by the L
-type calcium channel.
If this happens,
the myocyte behaves like
a slow response cell.
Depending on where this
happens, it could cause
atrial arrhythmia or
ventricular arrhythmia.
Tricked activity,
TA, is the oscillation
in member potential.
It requires a previous
action potential.
If it happens in later phase 2
or in phase 3,
it's called early after
depolarization, EAD.
If it happens in
phase 4, is termed
delayed after
depolarization, DAD.
EAD is typically associated
with action potential
prolongation, like in
Long-Cottie syndrome,
hypokalemia, etc.
EAD is due to reactivation
of the L-type calcium
channel, because these
channels are time-dependent.
As time passes, they
can be reactivated.
Since heart rate slowing
tends to increase QT interval,
the risk of EAD increases if
the heart rate is too slow.
DAD is associated
with calcium overload.
In conditions of
digital toxicity,
reperfusion-induced
arrhythmia and
catecholaminergic
polymorphic ventricular
tachycardia,
abbreviated as C-PVT.
As you have learned already
in action potential lecture,
calcium overload will
trigger sodium-calcium
exchanger. Activation
of sodium-calcium
exchanger will bring in
more positive charges
and depolarize the
membrane potential.
Fast heart rate typically
promotes calcium
overload and thus
increases DAD risk.
Abnormal impulse conduction.
First is the conduction block.
This is easy to
understand. Conduction
blocks are frequently
seen in these sites.
Sino-H exit block,
AV block, left
or right-bound
branch block, etc.
Another type of abnormal
impulse conduction is re-entry.
Since re-entry is considered
to be the most common
mechanism for all
tachyarysmias, this is an
important concept you have
to understand. Normally, a
heartbeat generated
inside the sinus node will
activate the atria, the
AV node, the His-Pukinji
system, and the ventricles
once, and then dies out.
In other words, one
heartbeat excites the whole
heart only once. As
shown in the left figure,
an impulse coming from
top will go down through
both left and right
pathways to reach the
bottom. The excitation
will not return back.
If the same impulse
re-excites the
heart more than once,
it's called re-entry
as shown in the
right illustration.
In the next slide, I'll explain
how the re-entry
could be formed.
To form a reentry,
first, it is necessary
to have inhomogeneous
cardiac tissues,
either anatomically
or functionally.
As shown in the left figure,
the left and right
pathways have different
conduction velocity
CV, and effective
refractory period
ERP. In other words,
they have different
electrophysiological
properties, or inhomogeneous.
The left side pathway
has slow conduction
velocity, or slow pathway,
but the slow pathway
has short ERP. The
right side pathway has
fast conduction velocity,
or fast pathway,
but it has long ERP.
Let's look how excitation will
be conducted in this case.
When excitation
comes from the top,
it will be conducted by
both the fast and the
slow pathways. Because
the fast pathway
conducts faster, it will
reach the bottom first.
The excitation conducted
by the fast pathway
could even invade into
the distal portion of the
slow pathway in a
retrograde manner. However,
when the two excitation
fronts, the anti
-grade conduction
by the slow pathway
and the retrograde
conduction from the
fast pathway collide,
the excitation
will stop and no re
-entry would occur.
This is the case with regular
beads A1, A1, A1
beads as shown.
Things will be different
when you have a short
preliminary bead A2, as
shown on the right figure.
At preliminary bead A2,
because the excitation
arrives so early,
the right side fast
pathway is not recovered
due to its long ERP.
Thus, the conduction will
be blocked in the fast
pathway, as indicated.
Since the left
side slow pathway
has short ERP and
recovers sooner,
the premature excitation
A2 can go down
along the slow
pathway to reach the
bottom, although
it conducts slower.
the right side fast pathway
could recover as time goes.
So when excitation travel down,
slowly through
the left side slow
pathway to reach
the bottom. And when
the right side fast
pathway recovers,
the excitation could
activate the fast pathway
retrograded from the
bottom. And when the
excitation reaches the
previously blocked area, and
if the area is already
recovered, then the
excitation could continue.
This forms a re-entry.
In other words, the
same excitation returns
back and re-excites
the tissue again.
Now you should
know these are the
requirements to form re-entry.
First, there should be
a unidirectional block.
As shown, the excitation
cannot propagate
from up-down, but it allows to
propagate in a reversed
direction. Second,
there is a slow conduction,
which affords time
for the previously
refractory tissue to recover.
Third,
there is a recovery
of previously
excited proximal tissue.
When all these requirements
are met, then reentry can form.
Here is the concept
of wavelength.
When re-entry happens,
in the re-entry circuit
there are two parts.
First is the tissue has been
excited and in refractory.
It's called wavelength. The
second part is tissue out
of refractory can be excited,
called excitable gap.
Wavelength is determined
by two factors,
the effective refractory
period ERP and
conduction velocity CV.
It can be calculated by
this equation, Wavelength
equals CV times ERP.
Since the re-entry
circuit equals
Wavelength plus Excitable Gap,
the Wavelength needs to
be less than the re-entry
circuit in order to sustain
re-entry. When wavelength
reaches the total length of
the circuit, then anything
will be in refractory and
reentry would be terminated.
From here, you should know
that by increasing wavelength,
it will decrease
reentry risk. On the
other hand, if you
shorten wavelengths,
then reentry risk increases.
This is why many antiarrhythmic
medications work to
increase ERP to increase
wavelengths and
decrease reentry.
If you still have
difficulty in understanding
the relationship
between wavelengths
and re-entry circuit,
I would like to give
you this analogy. Look
at this toy train.
You can envision
the length of the
train as the wavelength
and the length
of the track as the
re-entry circuit.
In order to run the train,
the length of the train
needs to be shorter than
the length of the track.
Otherwise, you cannot play.
On the other hand, if the
length of the train is very
short, then it's possible
that you can fit more than
one train on the track.
Hope this helps in
understanding the concept.
Since there is always an
excitable gap in reentry
circuit, if you can excite
the tissue in excitable
gap by artificial pacing
or electrical shock,
then you can stop the
reentry. This is one of
the important
electrophysiological features of
reentry allusion. It can
be terminated by pacing.
It's called anti
-tachycardia pacing.
Here are some of the
potential reentry circuits.
Panel A shows the model of
wavelengths and excitable gap.
B shows the Wolff-Parkinson
-White syndrome or WPW syndrome.
In WPW syndrome, there
is an accessory pathway
in addition to the normal
AV node hiss-bounded
pathway, linking the
atria and the ventricles.
The re-entry involves
both atria and ventricles,
the whole heart, so
it's a micro re-entry.
It's also an
anatomical re-entry
because there is an
accessory pathways.
Penelty shows re-entry
could happen at the
tiny junction of Purkinje
fibers and myocytes.
This shows the re-entry could
happen within the
muscle bundles.
These are micro re
-entries and could be
functional re-entries
without abnormal structure.
So re-entry can
happen in different
parts of the cardiac tissue.
Some may have very large
circuit like in WPW syndrome,
while some may have very
tiny circuit like in
atrioventricular node
re-entrant tachycardia.
Now we'll look at common
clinical allysmias.
First, we'll look
at blade allysmias.
The potential mechanisms
for blade allysmias are
failure of impulse generation
or decreased automaticity.
This includes sinus
bradycardia or sinus arrest,
typically seen in sick
sinus syndrome. mechanism.
The other mechanism
is failure of
impulse propagation,
or conduction block.
The common conduction
block sites
include sinoatrial
block, AV block, etc.
Now we'll look
at tachylysmians.
Tachylysmians are
caused by one or
more of these three
basic mechanisms,
abnormal automaticity,
trickle activity,
or re-entry. As
already discussed,
tachylysmians are divided
into supraventricular
tachylysmians and
ventricular alesimians.
Supraventricular
tachylysmians are
originated at the his
bundle or above. Because
the ventricles are
excited normally,
thus the QRS is typically
narrow with the exception
of pre-existing
ventricular abnormalities.
While the ventricular
tachylythmias are
originated below the his
bundle and are associated
with abnormal
ventricular activation,
the QRS complex will
be abnormal, widened.
This table lists
various supraventricular
tachyralesmias and
their mechanisms.
We will discuss some
of the important
supraventricular alesmias
in the next few slides.
First, we'll look
at atrial flutter.
It's known that
atrial flutter is
caused by a reentry
in the right atrium.
The reentry involves a
narrow region between
inferior vena cava and
the tricuspid valve.
This is known as the
cavil tricuspid isthmus.
As a result, casted
ablation of this
isthmus could be used
to cure this allysmia.
Next is atrial fibrillation.
Atrial fibrillation is
the most common clinically
significant allysmia.
Atrial fibrillation
is caused by multiple re
-entries in both atria.
Atrial fibrillation requires
a trigger or ectopic
fossa to initiate the
alethymia, and a substrate, the
remodeled atria, with
dilatation, fibrosis, to
support multiple re-entries
to maintain the alethymia.
In other words, in normal,
healthy subjects, it's
not easy to induce and
maintain atrial fibrillation.
Since most triggers are coming
from the pulmonary vein,
this is why pulmonary
vein isolation is used
to cure atrial
fibrillation in patients.
We'll look at
atrioventricular nodal
reentrant tachycardia,
AVNRT. By the name,
you should know the
mechanism is reentry.
In AVNRT patients,
the AV node region is
allegedly dissociated
into a fast pathway
and a slow pathway, so
-called AV node dual
pathway electrophysiology.
As we have discussed already,
a preliminary beat
is necessary to
initiate AVNRT as
shown in the figure.
Currently, cast ablation
of the slow pathway is
used to cure this alizmia
because because fast
pathway ablation has higher
risk to induce AV block.
Now we'll look at
atrioventricular
reentrant tachycardia, AVRT.
The arrhythmia is caused
by an accessory pathway,
or in some patients,
multiple accessory pathways
connecting the atrio
and the ventricles.
In Wolff-Pakinsen
-White WPW syndrome or
pre-excitation
syndrome, the accessory
pathway activation
can be seen on EKG.
However, in some patients,
the accessory pathways
could be concealed, meaning
the EKG could be normal.
Ablation of the
accessor pathway
is used to cure the arrhythmia.
In AVRT, depending on the
reentry circuit, if the
ventricles are activated
normally by the Purkinje system,
then the QRS complex
is normal or narrow.
If the range circuit
is reversed, ventricles
are activated by the
accessory pathway, then
the class complex is
abnormal or widened.
As a minimum, you'll have
to know WPW syndrome,
and you'll learn this in
EKG lecture, the changes,
the delta wave,
short PR interval,
and wide QIS complex.
Now we'll look at the
ventricular arrhythmia.
Ventricular arrhythmias
are always with
abnormal widened
QRS complex because
the ventricles are
activated abnormally.
We will look at premature
ventricular contraction PVC,
ventricular tachycardia and
ventricular fibrillation .
Premature ventricular
contraction can be caused
by any of these mechanisms,
abnormal automaticity,
triggered activity, or
re-entry, as shown here.
PVC results in wide
QIS complex on EKG.
Next, we'll look at
ventricular tachycardia, VT.
VT is typically divided
into monomorphic VT and
polymorphic VT, depending
on the shape of the
QRS complex. If the QRS
complex is more or less
the same, it's monomorphic
ventricular tachycardia.
If the QIS complex keeps
changing its shape,
it's the polymorphic
ventricular tachycardia.
Monomorphic
ventricular tachycardia
is typically seen
in patients with
structural heart
disease like ischemia,
non-ischemic
cardiomyopsy, alysmogenic
right ventricular
dysplasia. The mechanism
is predominantly
reentry. However,
some monomorphic VT
could also happen
in structurally
normal hearts called
idiopathic ventricular
tachycardia.
One type is outflow tract
ventricular tachycardia.
It's believed to be caused
by tricked activity.
Another type is
fascicular ventricular
tachycardia. It's
caused by reentry.
Polymorphic VT. In polymorphic
VT, the QRS complex
keeps changing. A specific type
of polymorphic VT is termed
to solder the points,
meaning twisting the points.
Polymorphic VT is
typically associated with
lung Coty syndrome, or
cardiac channel process,
like Blugger syndrome,
short Coty syndrome,
and catecholaminergic
polymorphic ventricular
tachycardia, CPVT.
Long-COTY syndrome include
inherited or congenital
Long-COTY syndrome and
acquired Long-COTY syndrome.
First, we'll look at the
congenital Long-COTY syndrome.
Many genetic mutations
have been identified in
congenital Long-COTY
syndrome. A majority, three
-quarter, is caused by
the first three types of
mutations, due to defects
in either potassium
channel or gain of function
of the sodium channel.
The mechanisms for Long
-Coti syndrome induced
ventricular arrhythmia
is triggered activity,
EAD, as we have discussed.
In these patients,
because sympathetic excitation
can exacerbate channel
abnormalities and further
prolong COT interval,
so beta blocker is typically
used to prevent the arrhythmia.
As a minimum, you
are required to know
the congenital Long
-Cottie syndrome.
Note that in some patients, the
channel defect is
poorly cardiac.
They have Long-Cottie syndrome,
but without other problems.
However,
in some patients, the
channel defect could also
affect sensory neuron
leading to hearing loss.
This is why when you
interview the patients,
you have to ask whether
the patients have
a hearing problem in
Lung-COTI patients.
Acquired Lung-COTI syndrome
refers to some people,
normally they have normal
COT interval. However,
when these people take
some medications or under
certain conditions, they
can develop lung COT.
These people may have some
subtle genetic defects.
This table lists some of
the common medications
or conditions which
may lead to Lung-CoT.
Note that here the
class 1C anti-arythmic
medication causes Lung
-CoT, not class 1B.
Here is the minimum
requirement for acquired
short QT syndrome,
especially these A, B,
C, D, E medications,
you have to know.
We'll look at
short QT syndrome.
This is opposite to
long QT due to gain of
function of potassium
channels, leading to
rapid repolarization.
In short QT patients,
the ventricules
repolarize faster with
very short AP duration
and QT interval.
The short action
potential duration results
in short ERP and
short wave lengths,
thus favoring formation
of multiple ranges.
Now we will look at the
Bluger syndrome. This is
due to diminished inward
sodium current, particularly
in right ventricular
outflow tract apicardium
region, leading to apicardial
dispersion of repolarization,
as shown in these
action potential traces.
In EKG, many patients
have characteristic EKG
abnormalities, as shown
here, a curve-type ST
segment elevation in
precordial leads V1 through
V3, which corresponds
to the RV or T region.
You are required to know
Blugard syndrome.
As shown here,
Blugard syndrome
patients have increased
risk to develop ventricular
tachylythmias and
sudden cardiac death.
Typically,
implantable cardioverter
defibrillator is needed
to prevent sudden cardiac
death in these patients.
Now we'll look at
catecholaminergic
polymorphic VT, CPVT.
This is due to genetic
disorders of calcium
release channels or
cardiac low-ending
receptor or their
controlling proteins.
In normal case,
low-ending receptor
should be closed
properly in diastole.
In CPVT patients,
the winding receptor is leaky,
like the leaky faucet here.
The leaky winding receptor
leads to elevated calcium
in diastole, thus activating
the sodium calcium
exchanger and leading to
DAD triggered activity.
CPVT is typically seen
in structurally normal
heart because sympathetic
excitation like exercise
or acute emotion can trick
CPVT. Beta blocker is
typically used to prevent
CPVT in these patients.
Finally, we'll look at
ventricular fibrillation
. Like in atrial
fibrillation, ventricular
fibrillation can be triggered
by any of these three
mechanisms and maintained
by the multiple re
-entries. When ventricular
fibrillation occurs,
the ventricles lose
coordinated contraction and
fail to pump blood, thus
the patient is dying.
Defibrillation is
the only effective
therapy to terminate
atrial fibrillation.
Here is the
question, what's the
mechanism for
defibrillation to work?
Because in ventricular
fibrillation,
there are multiple re-entries.
The electrical shock
can excite all excitable
gaps in multiple re
-entries. Thus, the
whole heart will be in
refractory and wait for
the sinus node to
initiate a new heartbeat.
That's the mechanism.
There are two terminologies,
cardioversion versus
defibrillation.
You have to know that
defibrillation is
used for ventricular
fibrillation only.
In this case,
the synchronizer button
should be turned off,
so the defibrillator
can deliver the shock
immediately once you place
the discharge button.
Because in ventricular
fibrillation,
the EKG signal may
not be large enough
to trigger the shock.
In other words,
the machine may not deliver
the shock if the synchronizer
is on during ventricular
fibrillation. Ventricular
fibrillation normally requires
higher energy compared
with cardioversion, while
cardioversion is used for
other tachyarrhythmias,
such as atrial fibrillation,
proxysmal superventricular
tachycardia, or even
ventricular tachycardia,
but not for ventricular
fibrillation. In this
case, the synchronizer
button should be turned
on and make sure it's
synchronized with the R
wave of the QRS complex.
Avoid not on the T
wave. That's important.
So, here is the another
question in cardioversion.
Why the shock should
be synchronized
with the R wave,
not the T wave?
As you know, the QRS complex is
produced by ventricular
depolarization.
The R wave indicates
that the ventricles
are depolarized and
in refractory is
the safest time to
deliver the shock.
If the shock is
delivered on T wave, then
ventricular fibrillation
could be induced because
from the peak of the T
wave to the end of the
T wave, the heart is
in a vulnerable period.
That's why you have to avoid
this period to
deliver the shock.
Here is the summary slide.
These are the contents
you have just learned
and expected to master.
Finally, here is
the link for your
feedback. Any comments
or suggestions are
welcome and thank you
for your attention.